<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A warning to the inhabitants of Barbadoes</title>
            <author>Rous, John, d. 1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92016</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2045</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42609</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">36282449</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 36282449</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150240</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92016)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150240)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2237:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A warning to the inhabitants of Barbadoes</title>
                  <author>Rous, John, d. 1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed on p. 8: John Rous.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Quakers --  Barbados.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150240:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A WARNING TO THE Inhabitants of <hi>Barbadoes,</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Who live in Pride, Drunkenneſſe, Covetouſneſſe, Oppreſſion and deceitful-dealings; and alſo to all who are found acting in the ſame exceſt of Wickedneſs, of what County ſoever, that they ſpeedily repent, and return from the evil of their wayes, and no longer make a ſport of wickedneſs but ſeek the Lord while he may be found, leaſt the Lord deſtroy them in his fury, and take them away in his anger, and give them their portion in utter darkneſs, (who now ſpend the day of their Viſitation careleſly, out of the fear of the Lord) where ſhall be weeping and wailing, and gnaſhing of teeth for ever.</p>
            <p>Alſo, ſomething to the Rulers of <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> that they rule right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and do juſtice on the wicked, who are Peace-breakers and Tranſgreſſors of the pure Law of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVritten by one who waits for the redemption of the Seed of God, and the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the wicked one, the man of ſin; written by a friend of Truth and Righteouſneſs,</hi> John Rous.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>OBardoes, Barbadoes!</hi> who excels in wickedneſs, pride and covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, oppreſſing, cheating and cozening, dreadful and terrible <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> practiſes; the Lord who is a conſuming fire and everlaſting burning will render to every one of you according to your wayes; horror and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> will take hold on you, you covetous ones, who ſtrive to get you care not how; who enlarge your Eſtates by violence, and encreaſe your wealth by wickedneſs; the cry of the oppreſſed is entred into the ears of the Lord of Sabbath, who will ſpeedily come to pour forth his plagues upon you, you wicked ones, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his righteous Judgements upon you who live in fraud and deceit, and act trecherouſly againſt your neighbors; the day is come nigh wherein you ſhall have no excuſe for your filthineſs, but the wrath of God ſhall be revealed in flames of fire againſt you, ye Earth-worms. Tophet is prepared of old, wherein ye ſhall be turned if ye repent not, and in that place you ſhall have doube re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned upon your heads; now if you ſlight the day of your viſitation, and go on in your ungodlineſs, heaping up wrath againſt the day of wrath, wherein God the righteous judge will render unto the wicked according to his works, then ſhall the goods which ye heaped together by violence and oppreſſion, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment you; and of the fury of the Lord God ye ſhall drink, who now do ſpend your time in ungodlineſs, and do make your hearts as adamant, and harden
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:150240:2"/>your fore-heads as braſs againſt the Lord, who hath given you a day to repent in; but unto you who ſpend your time in wantonneſs will the portion of the wicked be given, which is in the Lake which burns with fire and brimſtone for ever. Remember <hi>Dives</hi> you that truſt in your riches and deſpiſe the poor; your Riches will not ſave you from partaking of <hi>Dives</hi> portion, if you repent not, and turn to the Lord, and forſake your oppreſſion, pride and filthineſs wherein you are exalted.</p>
               <p>Wo unto you Drunkards, who are like Swine, wallowing in your filthineſs, and devouring the creatures upon your luſts, who think nothing good enough for your ſelves, but ſhut up your bowels of compaſſion towards them that want; the wants of the poor the Lord doth ſee; the cry of the hungry doth bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt you, ye Gluttons, who ſpend the creation on feaſting and rioting, but regard not the wants of the needy; you rejoice in the deſtruction of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and in your feeding without the fear of the Lord, but feed not the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry; how many have periſhed for want of the creatures which you have devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon your own luſts? how many have been murdered by many of you, by detaining of that which was neceſſary for them, from them? will not the Lord enquire for the blood of thoſe who have been deſtroyed through your hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartedneſs; yea the day is coming wherein the Lord will inquire diligently for their blood; then wo unto you oppreſſors and tyrants, you gluttons and drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards; for the Lord will return double to you if you deſpiſe this the day of your Viſitation; you gather together, and rejoice in ſpending the creatures which you have gathered upon your luſts; you eat and drink, and riſe up to do that which is wicked, and ſay in your hearts, <hi>Shall we be controubled by any one? or who ſhall have dominion over us?</hi> ye eat and drink, and ſpend your time in vanity, but remember not that the Lord will viſit you for theſe your ungodly actions; and if you turn not from theſe your evil wayes your portion ſhall you have in utter darkneſs, where ſhall be weeping, wailing, and gnaſhing of teeth for ever.</p>
               <p>Howl you proud ones, who are exalted in your own ſtrength; the day is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yea and near at hand, wherein the Lord will ſtrip you of your pride, and take away your glory, and ſhame and confuſion ſhall cover you, ye that beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the outſide, and deck your ſelves with dainty colours, and new invented faſhions, that men may admire your beauty, and honor you for your gay clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; dreadful and terrible will the day of the Lord be to you; how beautiful will you be when the juſt judge ſhall appear? And know you careleſs ones, who are at eaſe in the fleſh, ſporting your ſelves in the day time, the Lord will ſtrip you of your beauty, and inſtead of joy and lightneſs of heart, ſhall you have ſadneſs and mourning for ever, if you repent not; your glory and your beauty is odious unto the Lord, he hates your painted outſides, your fashions are abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to him; and you that now deſpiſe the beauty which is acceptable in the ſight of God, even the forſaking uncleanneſs, and departing from wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and walking in that which is juſt and upright; you shall have inſtead of beauty, burning, and inſtead of eaſe, ſorrow, howling and lamentation, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150240:2"/>of flattering one another in your deceit (as now you do) you ſhall with one conſent curſe the day of your birth, and howl and lament for the wo and miſery that ſhall come upon you.</p>
               <p>Now ſeek the Lord while he may be found; <hi>To day if you will hear his voice, harden not your hearts, go not on ſtill in your wicked practices, and ſpend not your time now in idle vanities, leſt you be taken away in the midſt of your pleaſures, and be caſt into the Pit, from whence there is no redemption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And all you young men and young women, who have not yet acted in the ſame exceſs of wickedneſs, as you Parents have done, whereby they have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked the Lord to anger, and have rebelled againſt the holy one of Iſrael; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member your Creator in the dayes of your youth, and ſpend not your time in vanity; take heed unto that which checks you in ſecret when you do that which is contrary to God; minding it, his will lead you out of the wayes of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and you will come to ſee wherein your forefathers turned aſide from the counſel of the Lord, and have deſpiſed the love of God, and have crucified the Lord of Life; hearkning unto that which checks and reproves for ſwcaring and lying, ſcoffing and ſcorning, and ſpeaking evil of the things you know not; you will come to ſee that which leads out of it and leads into the way of God; and that thoſe who are out of the way of God, have no right to the Promiſes that are made to the righteous; and look not at thoſe that are elder then you as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to do wickedly, but wherein that which is unclean and contrary to God is diſcovered and manifeſted unto you, forſake it, leaſt you walking in the pathes of the wicked, and forſaking the way of the juſt, with the wicked be condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; do not do wickedly becauſe your Elders do ſo; but in the time of your youth ſeek after the Lord, that you may be hid when he ſhall rent in pieces and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy thoſe that deſpiſe his commands, and will none of his reproofs; though you be young, yet is there ſomething that teſtifies againſt ſin in you, which doth condemn you when you act that which is unjuſt, and do to others that which you would not be done to your ſelves; living and abiding in this, you ſhall be examples to thofe that be old; and keeping to that which is juſt, in moderation and ſobriety, you shall exceed thoſe who have lived many yeers, and have ſpent their time in vanity; better is it to forſake the vanity and pleaſures of your youth, then ſpending your time in vanity, to come to repent when it is too late.</p>
               <p>O be not vain in your minds, nelther be exalted in that which will not frand, but ſeek after the Lord, that in his will you may come to delight, and in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence you may come to rejoice.</p>
               <p>And you whoſe Parents are great in the Earth, and do ſeek to make you great in the Earth alſo, take heed to your ſelves, ſeek not the pleaſures of this world, for they will indure but for a time: I have ſeen the pleaſures of this world, and I know what it is to rejoice in the world, and what it is to delight in vanity, and have ſeen the end of all this, That it is but vanity, and folly, and madneſs; for if one ſhould enjoy what heart can defire, yet an end of that would come, and a time when that joy ſhall be left, when the beauty of earthly things ſhall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150240:3"/>fade away; then will ſorrow and trouble take hold of all thoſe that delight in earthly things, and have not delighted in the Lord. <hi>I have delighted in vanity, and ſet my heart upon folly; but bleſſed be the Lord I have forſaken it, and now do know I have a reward, though not in the earth, yet in that which will endure for ever; if I had lived in pleaſure, and ſpent my time therein, wo would have been the end of my pleaſures, and lamentation the end of my delight; but now is my joy in the denial of that which formerly I delighted in, and peace, and joy and delight I finde in forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that which formerly I lived in, which naturally all youth do eagerly deſire after: And ſo</hi> I <hi>deſire, That in the ſame in which</hi> I <hi>live, ye alſo who are young may come to live, that ſo no longer you may delight in the earth and earthly things, but ſeek after the Lord and the things that belong to your peace; ſeek not after riches in the earth, for riches make them wings and flye away; but lay up treaſures in heaven, which will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver decay: Seek not after the horror of the world, for that honor muſt be laid in the duſt; but ſeek that honor which is of God, which will endure for ever. Glory not in any thing which is below, for the Lord is coming to ſtain the glory of all fleſh; but ſeek ye the glory of God: Delight not your ſelves in youthful pleaſures, but delight in walking in that which will lead you to uprightneſs and a godly couverſation if you walk in it; this will ſhew you what is contrary to God, and will lead you to God who are faithful to it; but will be your eternal condemnation who deſpiſe it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And all you Enemies of God, who have made your bands ſtrong in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, who have made a Covenant with Hell and Death; who becauſe the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord are not ſpeedily executed have ſet your hearts to do wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; wo is me for you, ye hard-hearted ones, who have not hearkned to the Lord, but have been as deaf Adders, which have not heard, though the charmer charmed never ſo wiſely; you have made a mock of the Servants of the Lord, and have deſpiſed thoſe that have been ſent unto you; but have rejoyced in your own corrupt Teachers, whom ye have heaped up according to your own ungodly luſts; your Teachers will not ſtand in the day of the Lord, for they are in the ſteps of the falſe Prophets which the Lord ever ſent his Prophets to cry againſt; they are greedy dumb dogs, who lye down and love to ſlumber, who make a prey upon the people, their deſires are after the Earth, they ſeek the fleece, and not the good of the flock; they are ſuch as go in the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> and their deſires after the earth are large; long have they been teaching among you, and are you not ſtill as wicked as ever you were? They are not ſent of the Lord, therefore ſhall they not profit the people at all; though they be drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards and live in filthineſs, yet will you hold them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; the Lord abhors ſuch Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, for they ſtrengthen you in your wickedneſs by crying peace unto you when deſtruction is neer at hand; and when theſe Teachers are made manifeſt unto you by the children of the Light, and they are moved in love to your ſouls to declare againſt your deceit that is held up by you under the pretence of worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping God, theſe you take hold of as Tranſgreſſors and as your Enemies, though you have nothing to ſay againſt what they declare: How can you ſtand before the Lord? How will you ſtand in the day when he ſhall appear, when his Wrath ſhall burn as an Oven? Think you that God is not the ſame God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150240:3"/>wickedneſs as ever he was; ye cannot ſerve God and the Devil; be not deceived, God will be avenged of you who deſpiſe the day of your viſitation, and turn the grace of God into wantonneſs: You that now laugh ſhall mourn; and you that ſtill go on in wickedneſs ſhall howl and lament when ſorrow ſhall take hold on you, and miſery which ſhall have no end.</p>
               <p>O that you were wiſe to conſider! O that you would conſider and forſake your wicked actions, that ſo in the day of the Lords wrath you may be hid; for truly great is the abominations wherewith you have provoked the Lord to anger: Ye have multiplied your iniquities beyond many Nations; you have gone beyond the heathen, who have not heard of God; in your wicked curſed ſinful practiſes have you provoked the holy One of Iſrael; the heathen ſeeing your abominations which have dwelt among you, looking at you as to have more Knowledge, have committed the like filthineſs as you have done, and you have been to them as patterns and examples of wickedneſs: The Lords contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie is great with you.</p>
               <p>O ye Inhabitants of <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> you have exceeded the ſins of <hi>Sodom,</hi> the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations of the Heathen are found among you, and think you to eſcape the fury of the Lord if you ſtill go on in wickedneſs? O no; do not deceive your ſelves, for of the righteous Judge of Heaven and Earth, who will not condemn the righteous, nor acquit the wicked, ſhall you receive a juſt reward, even according to your abominations. O conſider betimes! be not as the horſe and mule, who are without underſtanding; let the love of God, and the patience of God draw you to obedience; you cannot eſcape the hand of the Lord if you ſtill walk with hard hearts and ſtretched out necks: Large hath the love of God been towards you, that for all your abominations he hath not conſumed you, but hath given you a time to repent, and hath ſent his ſervants among you to declare his Truth among you, and his will, that you might be left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excuſe; and you have deſpitefully uſed them, and have made a ſcoffe of what they have declared; ye cannot long ſtand, you cannot reign for ever; though you be exalted among the Stars, yet will the Lord bring you down, even to the duſt.</p>
               <p>Take heed, take heed, repent, repent ye ſturdy Oaks and tall Cedars; the Sword of the Lord is drawn, which is for the ſlaughter of his Enemies, and for hewing in pieces thoſe that deſpiſe his love; for the wickedneſſe of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> did the Lord deſtroy them with fire and brimſtone; and the ſame wickedneſs is found among you, and your ſin is far greater, in that you have deſpiſed the couniel of the Lord, and have delighted in iniquity above mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that hath been declared among you (O ye Inhabitants of <hi>Barbodoes</hi>) which was not declared in <hi>Sodom</hi> nor <hi>Gomorral;</hi> for if it had, it would not have been reſiſted, as it hath been among you.</p>
               <p>Tremble before the Lord you wicked ones; tremble before the Lord you op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors of the poor; tremble before the Lord ye Enemies of goodneſs, whoſe delight is in doing wickedneſs, and in acting that which is contrary to God: Ye perſecutors, ye perſecute Chriſt; for your enmity is not againſt the creature,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150240:4"/>but againſt the ſpirit by which the creature is guided; and becauſe you cannot reach that (for it is out of your reach) you ſeek by all means you can to caſt lyes and falſe accuſations upon the creature, and if it lay in your power you ſeek to deſtroy it; but bleſſed be the Lord, who is the preſerver of thoſe that truſt in him, that keeps thoſe that ſerve him, for he it is that preſerveth us out of the hands of unreaſonable men: Remember the portion of thoſe that ſaw Chriſt naked, and clothed him not; ſaw him hungry; and fed him not; a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and took him not in; and in Priſon, and viſited him not; their portion was Hell, prepared for the devil and his angels; and think you to fare better then them who live in the ſame wicked practices? and you do exceed them; for they were to depart into hell becauſe they did not ſhew kindneſs unto Chriſt; but you ſhew him all the unkindneſs that lieth in your power; you will not only keep from viſiting him in priſon, but you will ſeek to caſt him into priſon; you do not only ſee him a ſtranger, and not take him in, but you will (he being a ſtranger) caſt reproaches and falſe reports upon him, that none may take him in: O that you were tender to conſider of your ungodly practices, and ſeek for remedy while it may be had, for truly the day will come when it will be too late to repent: Shut not your eyes againſt the Light, ſtop not your ears againſt the voice of Equity, for if you do, the time ſhall come when you ſhall cry and ſhall not be heard.</p>
               <p>Wo is me for you, ye are a ſottish children, a people that delight in rioting and uncleanneſs; how often would the Lord have gathered you, but ye would not? Darkneſs hath been your delight, to keep company with whores have you rejoyced in; your love is gone after harlots, there is no love in you towards the Lord; from the higheſt to the loweſt is covetouſneſs loved, yea pride and oppreſſion is delighted in; and by your wicked practices are the hearts of the righteous made ſad; the proud man among you is accounted bleſſed: Will ye not yet conſider, O ye people! How long will ye delight in vanity, and rejoyce in ſetting your ſelves againſt the Lord; <hi>Ye cannot proſper in your way, your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires are to do lewdneſs; wickedneſs and unrighteouſneſs do ye delight in; but juſtice and uprightneſſe, purity and holineſs is made a laughing-ſtock among you; the ſimple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted ye deride as a fool; he that departs from iniquity ye look at as if ſome ſtrange thing had happened unto him; blood is found in the midſt of you, yea, the blood of the innocent, which cryes in the ears of the Lord; and he is riſen in much indignation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ungodly: VVherefore now take heed to your ſelves, for you cannot flye from his preſence, you cannot hide your ſelves from his all-ſeeing eye; ye who fight againſt the Lord ſhall be deſtroyed; you have not only reſiſted man, but ye have reſiſted the Lord of life; your hearts are made fat, you live at eaſe in the fleſh; but a day of ſorrow, a day of woe and miſery will ſpeedily come upon you; ye earthly-minded ones, who account gain godlineſs, who glory in that which is your ſhame, who are feeding your ſelves againſt the day of ſlaughter; wo is me for your wilfulneſs, you are a people who drink iniquity as an Ox drinks water, and draw iniquity with the cords of vanity: And this do I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to you in plainneſs of ſpeech, for I cannot flatter you in your wickedneſs as your Teachers have done for many yeers; but in plainneſs of ſpeech do I declare againſt your wicked Practiſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>From one who is a lover of your ſouls, but an utter Enemy to your curſed practiſes, known by the name <hi>Iohu Rous.</hi>
                  </signed> 
                  <dateline>Bardoes <date>10. d. of the 8. month. 1656.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:150240:4"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>TO you who are Rulers in</hi> Barbodoes <hi>am I moved to write; ſee that you turn not the Sword which is put into your hands againſt thoſe that do well, but againſt thoſe that do evil; ſo will you be a terror to the evil doers, and a praiſe to thoſe that do well: To the Light of Chriſt Jeſus in all your conſciences</hi> I <hi>ſpeak, by which you ſhall ſee if you abide in it, who are thoſe that do well, and who are thoſe that do evil; he that is in</hi> Cains <hi>way, in ſtrife, hatred, envy, and ſeeking after the reward of</hi> Balaam, <hi>he doth evil, and hath caſt the Law of God behinde his back, and is for judgement, and is condemned with the Light; now if any are moved of the Lord to declare againſt theſe blinde Guides, beware,</hi> I <hi>warn you from the Lord of taking hold on ſuch as peace-brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers and evil-doers; for he is a peace-breaker and an evil-doer who is in thoſe wayes that Chriſt cryed wo against, and the Law of God takes hold of him, and he is for judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the Light of Chriſt Jeſus in all your conſciences ſhall witneſs what</hi> I <hi>ſpeak to be true; the Prophets and Apoſtles were ſent of the Lord to declare againſt ſuch as ſought for their gain from their quarter, and did preach for hire, and divine for money, and did make trade upon the people, and if men did not put into their mouths, they did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare war againſt them, and ſuch as had caſt the Law of God behinde their backs, and theſe were upheld by the Powers of the earth; and becauſe the Servants of the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared againſt them, they (many of them) were put in Priſon and ſuffered much; now you will confeſs that theſe were not Chriſtian Magiſtrates, neither did they rule for God, but did with their power oppoſe him in his wayes, and perſecuted his ſervants for repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving both Magiſtrates Prieſts and people for their wickedneſs and idolatry;</hi> Jezabel <hi>threatned</hi> Elijah <hi>becauſe he was zealous for the Lord of Hoſts, and ſlew the Prieſts of Baal,</hi> 1 King. 19.2. Ahab <hi>cauſed</hi> Micajah <hi>to be put in Priſon becauſe he witneſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the falſe Prophets, and declared the truth as he had received it,</hi> 1 King. 22. Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah <hi>was put into the Dungeon becauſe he declared the word of the Lord faithfully,</hi> Jer. 38.1, to the 7. <hi>Ieſus Chriſt who was the dear Son of God, when he was manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in the fleſh, was crucified by the powers of the earth becauſe he ſpoke the truth; and</hi> Barabbas, <hi>who was a murderer, was let go, as you may read in the Scriptures. And by the Light I ſee the ſame ruling now as was then, that a drunkard may come to a houſe of VVorſhip, and ſtay there quietly; but if one come to witneſs againſt the deceit there committed, and ſpiritual wickedneſs in high places, he is ſtraightway taken hold on as an evil doer; are not you who live in their practices oppoſers of Chriſt ſo well as thoſe which Chriſt ſpoke of, who ſhould hale them out of the Synagogues, and bring them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Rulers for his name ſake? are ye not Enemies of God, ye who perſecute and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thoſe who come among you to declare against your falſe wayes? are you not in the ſame wayes as the Rulers and People were who perſecuted</hi> Stephen <hi>to death, and ſlew</hi> James, <hi>and impriſoned</hi> Peter, Silas <hi>and</hi> Paul <hi>for witneſſing againſt their falſe wayes and worſhips? and truly it is ſo come to paſs in this generation, that though he be a drunkard that is ſet up to be a Teacher, or a vain perſon, or a lyar, or a prophane one, yot if any come to declare againſt his filthineſs in obedience to the Lord, they are taken hold of as evil-doers; but the day is coming wherein the ſecrets of al hearts ſhall be made manifeſt, and you who are ſet to do juſtice ſhall be called to an account, for the power wherewith ye have been intruſted; remember the portion that the Lord will give to the evil Servant when he comes, who eats and drinks with the drunken; He will
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150240:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>cut him aſſunder, and will give him his portion with the hypocrites; there ſhall be weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and wailing, and gnaſhing of teeth; be not exalted in your own ſtrength, and make not your own wills your Law; but ſee that the righteous Law of God be exalted, which reſpecteth no mans perſon, but doth juſtly towards all, and doth take hold on the evil doer, whether he be rich or poor, high or low; for he that reſpects perſons commits ſinne, and is convinced of the Law as a tranſgreſſor, and is for judgement. Now you who are Rulers,</hi> I <hi>charge you in the preſence of the living God, That to the Law of God in your conſciences you take heed, which doth judge the King and the Beggar; the Ruler, and he that is ruled, for doing that which is contrary to Truth and Juſtice; by this if you are ruled, you rule for God; and he that is not obedient to you, is an evil doer, and the ſword of the Lord is againſt him, and he is condemned by the Light; but if you forſake the Law of God, then pride and oppreſſion is exalted, and the righteous are not regarded, but he that departs from iniquity is made a prey upon.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>JOHN ROUS.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
